Guide to the Treasurer, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Treasurer, Yale University, records
1700-1973
RU 151
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
357.5
(599 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, minutes, memoranda, reports, audits, ledgers, cash journals, student accounts and bills, estate files, investment accounts, and construction records of the treasurer documenting every aspect of Yale's financial history up to 1971.
Yale University. Treasurer
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 5-A (YRG 5-A), Records of Yale officers and offices responsible for financial and administrative functions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Series I: General Accounting Books, 1883-1966 is available on microfilm (51,405 frames on 76 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM124.
Series II: Bursar's Records, 1902-1941 is available on microfilm (95,828 frames on 62 reels, 16mm. and 5 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM96.
Existence and Location of Originals
Originals destroyed after filming.
Biographical / Historical
Since its inception in 1701, Yale has had a treasurer to oversee the expenses and income of the college, to keep accurate books of financial affairs, to collect fees from students and others, to advise on investment policy, to solicit and collect gifts, and in many ways to secure the institution's financial well-being. The responsibilities of the office grew over the course of the years. In the early days a treasurer and a steward handled all financial duties. Later years saw the additions of assistant treasurers, financial agents, cashiers, bursars, comptrollers, clerks, legal counsel, investment counselors, and real estate agents.
Scope and Contents
The massive sub-record group of Finance and Administration known as the Treasurer's Records (RU 151) contains the largest continuous set of records in the Yale Archives. Records from 1701 - 1971 document every facet of Yale's financial history. Included in the sub-group are the general summaries of receipts and expenditures and the minute details of charges to a student for breakage in the chemistry lab or the cost of a bath-tub fixture in Jonathan Edwards College.
From the beginning of its history in 1701 Yale has had a treasurer to oversee the expenses and income of the college, to keep accurate books of the financial affairs, to collect fees from students and others, to advise on investment policy, to solicit and collect gifts, and in many other ways to secure the institution's financial well-being. (See appendix A for a complete list of names and dates of Yale's treasurers, 1701 - 1971.) The responsibilities of the office grew over the course of the more than two centuries covered by these records. In the early days a treasurer and steward could handle all duties. These records chart the additions of assistant treasurers, financial agents, cashiers, bursars, comptrollers, clerks, legal counsel, investment counselors, and real estate agents, all to enable the treasurer's office to handle the ever increasing work load.
The complexity of the treasurer's duties is reflected in the records kept by the office and in the arrangement established for these records. The arrangement does not establish specifically what office or department under the treasurer generated which records (as would be correct archival procedure). This would have been impossible to establish since the records had no markings to indicate the office of origin. The records are now arranged in six series.
Series I, GENERAL ACCOUNTING BOOKS, contains the records created to account for all receipts and expenses of the college, both in summary form on an annual basis, as in the reports to the Yale Corporation, and on a day-to-day, item-by-item basis, as in the cash journals. Series II, BURSAR'S RECORDS, contains those records connected with the levying and collecting of student fees. Series III, CORRESPONDENCE, includes both incoming and outgoing letters dealing with all facets of the treasurer's office. Series IV, BENEFACTORS, encompasses the histories, registers, and other records, including wills, relating to gifts, donations, and bequests to the university. Series V, INVESTMENTS, includes the accounts of real estate, stocks and bonds, and other securities owned by the university and the reckoning of the income, i. e., rent, dividends, and interest, generated by these investments. Series VI, CONSTRUCTION RECORDS, is composed of contracts, specifications, estimates, bills, and other materials gathered in the oversight of the erection of Yale buildings. Each of the series is divided into numerous sub-series and further into sections. The contents and arrangement of each of these series is described in greater detail in the relevant series description.
Though the records span the period 1701 - 1971, the great bulk of material dates from 1833 - 1939. The sparse records in the early years can be explained in part by the passage of time and the erratic, often idiosyncratic nature of bookkeeping at that time. Later Yale treasurers instituted more and more standardized, careful practices for recording all necessary detail for an expanding institution. The unexpectedly small size of the twentieth-century records might stem from a greater willingness on the part of later treasurers to dispose of non-current records in order to create space in crowded offices.
Beginning in the 1930s the treasurer's office began depositing the records of this sub-group in the Yale University Library. Previous to that the records had been in the treasurer's office and were moved from building to building as the office moved. No doubt some records were lost in moves that took the personnel of the treasurer's office from the Trumbull Gallery (later called the Treasury Building) to Woodbridge Hall, Byers Hall, and 451 College Street.
The records sat for many years unorganized; though several archivists attempted to design a plan of arrangement, the great quantity of records (nearly 400 feet) frustrated these plans for processing. In 1979 when a plan of arrangement for the Yale Archives was instituted and record group numbers assigned, the treasurer's records were classified under the records of Finance and Administration (YRG 5-B). They were given the designation YRG 5-B (later reclassed as RU 151) to reflect the fact that in 1977 the treasurer's office had been reorganized under the newly designated vice president for finance and administration. (See appendix B for a table of organization for Finance and Administration.) The plan of arrangement made RU 151 a closed sub-group; since no new records would in future be added the records could be processed completely and finally. The records in RU 151 include only those treasurer's records on deposit in the library prior to 1979.
It should be noted that the vice president for finance and administration and the offices under him retained many financial records, similar to those in this sub-group, which date prior to 1979. As the archives receives these records they will be incorporated into archival record groups according to the new classification scheme, by office of origin. Therefore, audit work papers (1967-1980) received by the archives in October, 1980, are now filed under Auditing, YRG 5-C, though the same type of records are included in Series I of of YRG 5-B. Similarly an accession of real estate files (1940-1979) received in February, 1980, is now filed in YRG 5-A while real estate files, ca. 1722-1930, are included in Series V of YRG 5-B. (See appendix C for an outline of all the sub-record groups in YRG5.) No materials received from functioning offices will ever be added to RU 151.
The treasurer's office deposited many records with the archives that were technically not the records of the treasurer but had presumably been stored in the office for safekeeping or for lack of a better place to put them. A large number of letters to and from President Ezra Stiles came with these records but were removed from the records years ago. These are now part of the Ezra Stiles Papers in the Beinecke Rare Book Library. The Connecticut Education Society Records (# 1242), the Yale Gymnasium Corporation Records (# 1243), and the York Square Trustees Records (# 1250) now exist as separate distinct manuscript groups, each with its own register. Other records have been transferred to appropriate records groups in the Yale Archives.
Manuscripts and Archives has personal papers for several Yale treasurers, and these papers may contain additional records of the treasurer's office. See appendix A for a list of personal papers of Yale treasurers in Manuscripts and Archives.
All appendices referred to in the the description of the papers are available only in the print version of the finding aid. Please consult the reference archivist for assistance.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in six series: I. General Accounting Books, 1701-1971. II. Bursar's Records, 1727-1941. III. Correspondence, 1717-1940. IV. Benefactors, 1700-1963. V. Investments, 1722-1926. VI. Construction Records, 1752-1941. Folios. Subsequent accessions.
College buildings -- Design and construction; Endowments; Gifts; Investments; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Finance; Alling, John; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Ecklund, John E., 1916-2000; Farnam, William Whitman, 1844-1929; Gage, Charles Stafford; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Hillhouse, James, 1754-1832; Kingsley, Henry Coit, 1815-1886; Lynde, Nathaniel; McClung, Lee, 1870-1914; Prout, John, 1689-1776; Rosewell, Richard; Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793; Tighe, Laurence G., 1894-1954; Trumbull, John, 1750-1831; Tyler, Morris Franklin, 1848-1907; Warner, Wyllys, 1800-1869; Collegiate School (New Haven, Conn.); Yale College (1718-1887) -- Administration; Yale College (1718-1887) -- Finance; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Benefactors; Yale University -- Endowments; Yale University -- Finance; Yale University. Treasurer
- General Accounting Books, 1701-1971; Series I; 24; (58 boxes, 1 folio, 76 reels of microfilm)
  Conditions Governing Access note
  The materials are open for research.
  Scope and Contents note
  GENERAL ACCOUNTING BOOKS contains the records of the treasurer, which show, both in summary and in detail, all receipts and expenses of the college. The series is divided into four sub-series, as follows:
  Annual Reports and Audits (1776 - 1967)
  1701 - 1832
  1833 - 1971
  Miscellaneous Books
  The first sub-series contains those records which summarize the college's finances on a year-by-year basis. The records in the second and third sub-series were generated on a day-to-day basis and reflect different systems of accounting employed during the dates of the respective sub-series.
  Annual Reports and Audits (1776-1967) begins with the abstracted annual reports and the fuller annual audit reports from which they were extracted. Both are annual accounts of receipts and expenditures organized alphabetically by account. Each report was scrutinized and then signed by the auditor, before being presented to the Prudential Committee and Yale Corporation. The sub-series includes manuscript copies of the annual audit reports from 1829 - 1902. (A form of earlier annual accounts is filed in sub-series 1701 - 1832 )
  The corporation voted at its September, 1829 meeting, to print for the first time, a report on the financial state of the college. A complete set of these printed copies of the Treasurer's Report from 1829/30 to the present is available in the Manuscripts and Archives reading room catalogued as Y31. B1. The only printed copies of these reports now kept with the treasurer's Records are those containing special annotations and those with additional reports from the auditor, such as reports relating to cash control, matters of internal control, revisions of the accounting system, or surveys of accounting and budgetary procedures. These printed copies and supplemental reports follow the manuscript copies. There are also detailed statements of the treasurer's report filed here.
  The sub-series concludes with statements of college accounts submitted to the Connecticut General Assembly and working papers used in the preparation of these annual statements. The college reported to the General Assembly to show it how state funds appropriated for the benefit of the college were being used.
  The sub-series 1701 - 1832 encompasses the records of the college's early and rather primitive and erratic bookkeeping system. The records span the tenure of several treasurers, but the total quantity for this period is scant. During the period the treasurer was not the only administrative official handling and recording receipts and expenditures, and this sub-series also includes accounts kept by the president, assistant treasurer and steward.
  For most of this early period the major record of financial transactions is a ledger, often referred to as "Treasury Book A". Successive treasurers and other college officials made entries in this volume, which was then presented to the Corporation for approval. The most consistent account is that with the president and fellows of Yale College. These accounts serve as both a daily record and an annual reckoning. The volume also contains stewards" accounts and accounts with various individuals. An index in the beginning serves as a directory to these different accounts. The sub-series contains the original and two photocopies of this important volume.
  Though the dates of "Treasury Book A" span the years 1701 - 1828 the volume does not include all accounts for this period. Following "Treasury Book A" are several other ledgers that either fill in accounts missing from or overlapping accounts in "Treasury Book A". Accompanying these ledgers are many supporting vouchers for the recorded transactions.
  In 1803 Stephen Twining became assistant treasurer, but it is unclear how Twining and Treasurer James Hillhouse defined their respective duties. Until 1810 Hillhouse was in Washington serving in Congress. It appears that Hillhouse's duties as treasurer were advisory and that much of the work devolved upon Twining. The accounts in Twining's hand are definitely more numerous. Three ledgers kept by Twining date from 1805 until his death in 1832. Some of the confusion of duties may be reflected in an annual statement of the account between Hillhouse and Twining in order to keep the books in balance.
  The sub-series includes two cash journals, an account book that became a standard form for recording each credit and debit. One of these journals is in the hand of William G. Hooker, a clerk in the office who assumed the management of operations after the death of Twining. The sub-series also includes a volume of trial balances. This form of daily balancing of income and expense also became a standard bookkeeping procedure later. The two registers of orders drawn on the treasurer are similar to counterfoils of checkbooks. They list by account the check or order drawn on that account. These registers date to 1837, but this form does not seem to have been continued.
  The sub-series concludes with several scattered accounts supplied by the steward for expenses incurred in providing food for the commons and in paying sweepers of college rooms and receipts of payments for these services. (The actual accounting of individual student bills and payments for board and sweeping are found in Series II.) Since Stephen Twining served as steward as well as assistant treasurer his steward's accounts are found interwoven in his ledgers and are not distinguishable separately.
  Both James Hillhouse and Stephen Twining died in 1832. At the May, 1833, meeting of the Yale Corporation the Prudential Committee and the new treasurer, Wyllys Warner, were directed to "devise and report a proper scheme for the management of the Treasury Department." The growing complexity of treasury accounts, including separate books for the Medical Institution and the Theological Department, bookkeeping for the more aggressive fund raising projects and the complete change of personnel in the treasurer's office made 1833 an ideal time for instituting a new system of accounts. The new system would be modified and expanded but certain basic forms can be traced from 1833 to the present. The sub-series 1833 - 1971 includes the records of the new system.
  It is unfortunate that Wyllys Warner's report on the new "proper scheme" was not recorded in the corporation minutes since a first hand explanation of the workings of the system would have produced a clearer understanding of these records. The newly instituted system followed the developing method of double- entry bookkeeping and involved the use of daybooks, cash journals, and summary journals and ledgers to record all transactions as well as trial balances and balance sheets to test the accuracy of the books and summarize the financial situation from day to day, month to month, and year to year. All of these types of books are represented in the sub-series 1833 - 1971.
  The most detailed record of transactions will be found in the daybooks and cash journals and their supporting vouchers. Daybooks were the books of original entry for every transaction; each transaction was recorded as it occurred. The cash journals are a similar chronological recording of all monies received and paid out but with debits arranged on a facing page from the credits and in later years in separate volumes for cash receipts and cash disbursements.
  All the supporting vouchers, in the form of bills and receipts, have been placed after the cash journal in which they are recorded. The vouchers are arranged as they appear on the page of the cash journal and not by the date of the bill, since bills were often paid many months after they were issued. There is not a complete set of vouchers for any cash journal and after 1884 there are none at all. For any one year an estimated 70% of the bills have survived. There are far fewer receipts. Only for the fiscal year 1883/84 are the bills nearly complete.
  Two types of balance books were found in this period, "trial balances" and "cash settlements". It is not clear exactly why the two types were needed. It may be that the "trial balances" balanced monies recorded in the cash journal and that the "cash settlements" were used to keep account of several different cash accounts. Entries such as "American Education Society" or "Trinity Church" lead one to surmise that some monies passed through the hands of the Yale treasurer but were neither debits nor credits on the Yale books and that the Yale treasurer acted as a collecting agent only.
  The general journals and ledgers that follow in the sub-series are the backbone of the double entry system. The general journal is a summary chronological recording device for all transactions; transactions are classified as debits and credits according to the accounts to which they will be posted in the ledger. Entries in the journal and postings in the ledger indicate page numbers which cross reference one to the other. The ledger contains a summary record of the transactions but it is arranged according to account and then chronologically within that account. Ledgers have an index to enable the user to find the needed account. The Treasurer's Records contain paper copies of both journals and ledgers only to 1912. The twentieth century volumes were quite large and bulky and were, therefore, microfilmed, after which the originals were destroyed. (See appendix D for a guide to the microfilm.) The balance sheets, some yearly, some monthly, which were prepared from the ledgers to show the condition of each account, follow.
  The Miscellaneous Books sub-series concludes with a few miscellaneous books, including the treasurer's schedules and memoranda books. There is also a curious ledger and journal for what seems to be a short-lived Yale bank for individual depositors in the mid-1840s. The large volumes in Miscellaneous Books have been microfilmed and the originals destroyed. Included among the volumes on film are detailed university payrolls.
  - Annual Reports and Audits
    - Abstracts (also includes accounts of Elizur Goodrich, assistant treasurer, 1797-1800; other accounts, ca. 1800 with supporting vouchers), 1796-1882 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Abstracts: loose copies, 1806, 1818-1829, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abstracts, 1883-1902 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Annual audit reports, circa 1756-1828
      General note
      See: box 12, folders 54-56
    - Annual audit reports: loose copies, 1829-1832 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Annual audit reports., 1841-1889 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - Annual audit reports., 1890-1902 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1908-1909, 1914-1917, 1931-1935/1936 (Box 4, Folder 11-16)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1936/1937-1943/1944 (Box 5, Folder 17-24)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1944/1945-1949/1950 (Box 6, Folder 25-30)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1950/1951 - 1955/1956 (Box 7, Folder 31-36)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1956/1957 - 1959/1960 (Box 8, Folder 37-40)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1960/1961 - 1962/1963 (Box 9, Folder 41-43)
    - treasurer's Report: printed copies, 1963/1964-1964/1965, 1966/1967 (Box 10, Folder 44-46)
    - State of the college accounts exhibited to the Connecticut Colony General Assembly, 1766, 1767, 1769, 1773 (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - State of the College for the year ending September 9, 1767
      See: Anson Phelps Stokes papers, mss. group no. 229, box 193, folder 423
    - Reports of receipts and expenditures for the Connecticut General Assembly, 1799-1828 (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - Working papers for annual reports of receipts and expenditures with summary reports for the Connecticut General Assembly, 1851-1870 (Box 11, Folder 49-51)
    - Working papers for annual reports of receipts and expenditures with summary reports for the Connecticut General Assembly, 1871-1881 (Box 12, Folder 52-53)
  - 1701-1832
    - Ledger, "Yale College Treasury Book A": photocopy, 1701-1828 (Box 12, Folder 54)
    - Ledger, "Yale College Treasury Book A": photocopy, 1701-1828 (Box 13, Folder 55)
    - Ledger, "Yale College Treasury Book A": original, 1701-1828 (Box 13, Folder 56)
    - Bills, receipts, and accounts for period recorded in ledger, "Yale College Treasury Book A", 1701-1828 (Box 14, Folder 57-61)
      See also: folio 58a, folder 1
    - Ledger style accounts of John Prout, 1756, 1759-1765
      See: folio 58a, folder 2
    - Ledger style accounts compiled by Elizur Goodrich, 1782-1783 (Box 14, Folder 62)
    - Ledger style accounts compiled by Elizur Goodrich, 1797-1800
      See: box 1, folder 1
    - Ledger containing Stephen Twining's daybook for the college account, 1805-1817, and sundry accounts with students and faculty, 1799-1803 (includes supporting vouchers), 1799-1817 (Box 14, Folder 63)
    - Ledger, "Yale College Treasury Accounts", with supporting vouchers, 1817-1823 (Box 14, Folder 64)
    - Ledger, "Yale College Treasury Accounts" (also called "College Day Book") with supporting vouchers, 1823-1832
      See: box 58, folder 419
    - Stephen Twining in account with the President and Fellows of Yale College: annual summary compiled from the ledgers, 1809-1832
      See: box 58, folder 420
    - James Hillhouse in account with Stephen Twining: annual statements, 1801-1811, 1818-1828 (Box 15, Folder 65)
    - Cash journal, 1826 September 15-1831 February 3 (Box 15, Folder 66)